Ever since I started discussing creatine
over a decade ago now, the same question
has popped up over and over and over
again. Does creatine cause hair loss?
Unfortunately, there weren't any studies
discussing the topic. So, no one had any
definitive answers. And even more
unfortunate, the one study that I was
aware of that was going to answer that
question was cancelled. I believe it was
supposed to start in April of 2020. And
we know people weren't going anywhere
during that time. Yet, I was pleasantly
surprised to find out a different trial
was underway to answer this plaguing
question. So, let's get into it. The
idea behind the creatine causing hair
loss stems from a study that released in
2009 that has nothing to do with hair
loss. Are you confused? So, are most
people that know about this study
because somehow it was twisted into
creatine likely causes hair loss. Now,
to be fair, the mechanism behind the
headline makes some sense, and it's
related to this study. Prepare to jump
some hoops. The study indicated that
creatine increases the rate of
conversion of testosterone to its much
more potent brother molecule,
dihydrotestosterone, DHT. The reason
this is applied to a hair loss is that
DHT can bind to receptor and create a
complex that allows the hormone to bind
genes inside the nucleus of your
follicle cells in your skin. The nucleus
is where the majority of our DNA or
genes are kept. As a result, this
binding to specific genes can lead to
the expression or the production of new
molecules. Unfortunately, DHD encourages
the production of cell death and hair
growth suppression genes. So that's
where the idea came from that creatine
reduces hair growth. Although, and this
is important, hair growth was never
measured. There's one more critical
piece of information on this that we
need to discuss, but I'll get to more of
that in a bit. For now, let's pop open
the new study that's actually measuring
creatine's impact on hair loss. In this
study, the researchers randomly
allocated people to consume a placebo, a
non-creatine substance, or creatine for
12 weeks. Then they tested their blood
as well as importantly hair growth and
hair density to see if hair grew more
slowly or shed. Interestingly, they did
see an increase in the ratio of DHT to
free testosterone, meaning there's more
DHT relative to free testosterone than
there was before. The bluish line in
placebo and the reddish line is creatine
before and after. But a few things here.
One, if we look at the DHT levels,
there's no increase. And in fact, the
change occurs from a drop in free
testosterone before everyone freaks out
and starts accusing creatine of
castrating people. The second caveat
here is that the placebo condition
experience the exact same effects. So
this is nothing unique to creatine.
Okay. What about hair loss, though? Here
we go. On the left, we see the hair
count and on the right, we see the
density of hair. The individual dots are
the individual results of each
participant. And the average result, all
data combined, is where the lines lead.
I'll just uh spoil it. There's no effect
on hair count, hair density, and
although I'm not showing it to you here,
other metrics like of hair growth and
different stages of hair growth were
unaffected. No matter how you slice it,
creatine has no effect on
hair. After 15 years, I was wondering if
I was a, you know, maybe a thinning up
here. But there is one major
consideration that this study doesn't
address, which could still hold the door
open for the possibility. I suppose I
should disclose that I'm a creatine
shill. I snort it. I bathe in it. I pay
my taxes in it. So much so I wrote a
book on the molecule and although I
don't sell it anymore, it is available
for everyone with the Physionic Insider
membership. That's right folks, we're
here again. The Physionic Insiders,
where we laugh and love and sleep on
creatine pillows, but also you get
access to all my research reviews, a
whole video archive, a private podcast,
a live sessions with me, myself, and I.
And you can join using the link in the
description. I'll see you over there.
And yes, I'll bring the
creatine. There are three things to
consider in relation to this study.
Numero, this study looks at people in
general, but I think one of the
arguments for creatine hair loss angle
is the fact that it might affect people
who are genetically predisposed to hair
loss, a specific type called androgenic
alopeescia. So, this study doesn't
exactly answer if people with a family
history of balding are going to speed
that process up with creatine
consumption. Specifically, those with a
family history of their hair loss due to
androgenic exposure. That's testosterone
and dihydrotestosterone that we
discussed earlier have greater local or
scalp activity of the enzyme responsible
for the conversion of testosterone to
DHT called five alpha reductase type 2.
Unfortunately, this study because it was
a small sample, so a small number of
people and didn't do any genetic testing
or family history checks can't answer if
these people are still more susceptible
to creatine. Numero do the study was
only in men and considering the subject
of hormones, it makes this impossible to
extend to women as well. We'd need
another study for that. Numeiro Tua.
It's a 12-week study, so it may not be
long enough to detect an effect. Now, I
don't believe that because considering
the measurement, hair growth, and hair
number, we'd likely see an effect even
in a small sample across 3 months. So,
will your hair fall out if you consume
creatine? The answer is finally here,
and the evidence now leans moderately
strongly to no for most people. and an
uncertainty remains related to people
who may have a genetic predisposition,
but there's also no direct evidence
suggesting that it would affect them
either. I did mention that I'm a
creatine shill, and you can be too if
you simply learn of all the incredible
effects creatine has in your body. You
could start your indoctrination right
here. See you there.